<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Humble advise to the right honorable the lord mayor, the recorder, and the rest of the justices of the honorable bench to the goodmen of the jury, aud [sic] at the Sessions House in the Old-Bayley, London, in behalf of Mr. John Bidle, prisoner in Newgate.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42339</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36273029</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36273029</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150094</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86726)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150094)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2230:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Humble advise to the right honorable the lord mayor, the recorder, and the rest of the justices of the honorable bench to the goodmen of the jury, aud [sic] at the Sessions House in the Old-Bayley, London, in behalf of Mr. John Bidle, prisoner in Newgate.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Biddle, John, 1615-1662. --  Twofold catechism.</term>
               <term>Unitarians --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Unitarianism --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150094:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN HUMBLE ADVISE TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE LORD MAYOR, THE RECORDER, And the reſt of the IUSTICES of the Honorable Bench.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>To the goodmen of the Jury, and at the Seſsions Houſe in the</hi> Old-Bayley, London, <hi>in behalf of</hi> Mr. John Bidle, <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in</hi> Newgate.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce with the Aged there is Wiſdome, and with grey hairs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, it were a ſin to doubt your readineſſe to hear, and apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to conſider, what the meaneſt hath to offer, by way of clearing your paſſage in ſo dangerous a road as you are entering into, if you ſhall proceed to the Triall of this learned Lamb like Chriſtians, Mr. <hi>John Bidle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though for other cauſes experience may have fortified your judgements, ſo as Adviſe may ſeem preſumption, yet in that you have cauſe to doubt and to fear, that you are preſſed with theſe or the like ſnares, through the ſubtil lyings in wait, by which many holy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and precious mens lives have (even in this place) been cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly taken away. So therefore when you read the Books of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of the Primitive times, and of thoſe in the bloody daies of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> or of the leſſer ſanguin daies of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> you rejoyce with exceeding joy as you run over theſe ſad ſtories; finding none of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150094:2"/>
your Predeceſſors hands in thoſe bloody Councels or proceedings, and would not for to gain the world be your ſelves guilty of the like. Let therefore your proceedings be with circumſpection, leſt afore you are aware, you are intangled paſt hopes, and do the things you have ſo much loathed in others.</p>
            <p>And though you may all ſtand clear in this matter in the ſight of God, both in the preſent and for all future times be pleaſed, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your ſeveral places, to conſider what thoſe things are, wherein perſons in the like places, and in the like caſes, have been uſually miſled, and it will appear in all times, as in the preſent, that the firſt evil which attends the Magiſtrates to incite and ſtir them up againſt conſcientious perſons, is the miſtaken or unin formed zeal of Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, (of which no time was ever wanting) who having got an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, or Act of Parliament, the Decree of a Councell, or Aſſembly of Divines, declaring ſuch or ſuch opinions to be Blaſphemous, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, or Schiſmatical, think they need no more for their warrant, but preſently fall to their buſineſs, watching and ſpying over the works and writings of conſcientious perſons. Thus having by an uncomely or unhandſome kind of diligence gotten ſomething, which they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Parliament Laws judg Blaſphemy, inſtantly they run therewith unto the Magiſtrate, crying out Blaſphemy, Blaſphemy, never ſuch Blaſphemy ſince the world was created, name the perſons, the place, the writings, and cry out for Juſtice, which in their ſenſe, is a preſent ſeizure, and impriſonment of the perſon thus cried out on.</p>
            <p>What a ſtrait now in this caſe is the Magiſtrate in, if he enquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Juſtice of the Law, or the nature of the opinion againſt which Blaſphemy is cried, or after the peaceableneſs of the Party, or his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſeableneſs or readineſs to appear, if he incline to ſend gently for him, and uſe not the utmoſt rigour his authority can warrant; he likewiſe for his meer ingenuity and humanity herein, incurs the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of favouring Heretikes, Schiſmatikes, and Blaſphemers, ſo as the Magiſtrate, even againſt his own inclinations, is as it were ſurprized, and inforced by importunate elamors, to deal with godly peaceable people oftentimes, as with the moſt notorious Thieves, Harlots, and Murtherers, ſending for them by like Warrants, and no nay, but Bail muſt be refuſed, ſent to the ſame infamous priſons, as this Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> to <hi>Newgate,</hi> to be tried for his life as a Blaſphemer.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt evil the Magiſtrate is liable to in occaſions of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and is the cauſe of all ſucceeding evils, and being ſo, how neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary is it for all Honorable perſons in Authority to ſtand upon their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150094:2"/>
Guard againſt ſuch dangerous aſſaults as theſe, which if yeelded unto, in the end draweth on them that fearful ſentence, <hi>James</hi> 5. 6. <hi>Ye have condemned and killed the juſt, and he doth not reſiſt you;</hi> a heavy ſentence, and due to too many of your Predeceſſors in this place, for want of a timely and conſcionable conſideration of the dangerneſs of the thing they had in hand, God evert it from your Honorable Society.</p>
            <p>All agree that it is beſt to kill temptation in the bud, and therefore to be provided againſt theſe clamorous onſets, is the beſt part of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, to which end it is requiſite to be skilful in the conditions of theſe, (viz. Mr. <hi>Thomas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill, Luke Faune, Nathanael Webb,</hi> and <hi>George Calvert)</hi> and the like Informers alſo in the true nature of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, and to be able to diſtinguiſh of opinions, and to try them by ſome more certain Touchſtone, then by the imperfect Vote of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Synods, Councels or Aſſemblies, al which have moſt groſly erred, frequently condemned Truth for Error, nay eſtabliſhed Error by a Law, and ſuppreſſed the moſt certain Truths, by which the moſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and godly in this Nation have under pretence of Law, which is grievous injuſtice been baniſhed, impriſoned, tormented, &amp; murthered.</p>
            <p>As to the condition of theſe Informers, how good an eſteem ſoever ſome may have of them, yet they are very like unto thoſe tumultuous perſons in <hi>Acts</hi> 16.19. who caught <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> and drew them into the Market place unto the Rulers, and brought them to the Magiſtrates, ſaying, <hi>Theſe men, being Jews, do exceedingly trouble our City, and teach cuſtoms which are not lawful for us to receive, nor to obſerve, being Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi> Here was a ſpecious pretence, as if the trouble of the City lay heavy at their hearts, and ſet the men to complain; and it is like enough the Magiſtrates believed them to be well-meaning people, zealous of the good and quiet of their Country, nor ever had been otherwiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, but that it pleaſed the holy Spirit of God, for diſcovery of ſuch Hypocrites, and for forewarning all Magiſtrates againſt ſuch cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous deceivers, to demonſtrate in the 16. <hi>v.</hi> that the true cauſe of their complaint was the loſs of their gains, which they wickedly made out of the Damſels evil Spirit of Divination, whom <hi>Paul</hi> caſt out. Whereunto agreeable is that alſo of <hi>Demetrius,</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 19. where their gain by making ſhrines being in danger to be taken away by <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine, he and his Accomplices ſticks not by his clamors to put the whole City into an uproar; ſo you ſee it is no new thing, for fear of loſs, and hope of gain, to move the Springs of the heart with a wicked ſuggeſtion, when the tongue and face ſpeaks nothing but Religion and publike zeal; and if the ways of Informers in all former Ages were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150094:3"/>
looked into, even from the Perſecution in the Primitive times, to the times of <hi>John Huſs, Jerom</hi> of <hi>Prague, William</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and throughout all the daies of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> Qu. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>Charles,</hi> (through all which times, more or leſs, there was perſecution for Conſcience) it was groſly manifeſt, that fear of loſs, and hope of gain, were the only or chief motives to all the Informers, ſo as at beſt it renders theſe ſuſpected, and they may be as guilty as any of the former, though they themſelves perceive it not, for the heart is deceitful above all things, nor doth any thing benum the conſcience, and blind the underſtanding ſo much, as fear of loſs, and hope of gain.</p>
            <p>And if theſe mens ways be thought on, it will be more then proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that they are not clear in this matter, being for the moſt part Bookſellers; it's known that Books of Divinity are their chiefeſt ſale, both in Sermons and other Treatiſes, and that they buy, and ſomtimes pay dear for their Copies. Now the opinions which are charged upon Mr. <hi>Bidle,</hi> are croſs and contradictory to the grounds of their moſt ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Copies, and to the main part of their ſale, and conſequently threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens their gain: Is there not then a ſtrong provocation upon their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to withſtand ſuch Doctrines, and to take up the ſame courſe to do it, by ſtirring up the Magiſtrate to impriſon and put to death ſuch Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, for leſs they cannot call him, to have him effectually ſilenced.</p>
            <p>If it be not thus, why of all ſorts of men that daily have heard and read Mr. <hi>Bidles</hi> judgment, without trouble or regret of mind, nay (though not of his judgment, yet honoring and highly eſteeming of him for his manifeſt piety of life and great learning) why ſhould the Traders in books be ſo violent againſt him, as that nothing but his life will ſatisfie them? Why have not ſome of thoſe who often hear him? Why not ſome of the private Churches, that are moſt of them oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in judgment? Why have not they perſecuted him, and in deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his opinions forced him before the Magiſtrates, ſo to priſon and perſecute him to the death? Do they all of them, and all other conſcientious people want zeal to God, to Chriſt, and to the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to ſet them on? Nay, why ſtartle they not, but on the contrary, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the gathered Churches, and other well-affected perſons, petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Highneſs appear againſt his moleſtation, and earneſtly preſs for his liberty; but becauſe they know whatever his judgment is, the way to make him of another belief, is not by impriſonment or fear of death, (Chriſt nor his Apoſtles having left any ſuch rule) but by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the points in difference to be freely diſputed and examined, and as <hi>the noble</hi> Bereans, <hi>to ſearch the Scriptures, whether thoſe things are</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150094:3"/>
               <hi>ſo or no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Som what muſt be the matter that theſe Bookſellers thus beſtir themſelves above others, wherefore it is the beſt and ſafeſt courſe for the Magiſtrate upon ſuch ſtrong preſumption, to provide againſt the worſt, and to conclude them at beſt but dangerous Informers, moſt pernicious counſellors, and not in the leaſt to be ſwayed by their ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretences of zeal, but to ſuſpect all their ſuggeſtions, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from covetous and corrupt hearts; for were they indeed ſo ſenſible of Chriſts Honor as they would be thought, certainly you would find them firſt purging their own ſhops of all kinds of Popiſh, and wanton ſcurrilous books, invented purpoſely to corrupt and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate youth, or if they can excuſe themſelves herein, which ſome will not credit, yet they cannot but know ſuch as thoſe are thick and three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſold round about them, and yet their zeal burns not that way at all, the reaſon whereof, what can it be, but that it oppoſeth not their way of gain, elſe would not they offer one Petition more in behalf of the Proteſtant cauſe, for the ſuppreſſing ſuch Books, and the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning ſuch perſons as writes them, who nautiate youth, and hath no pretence of Conſcience from the Word of God to ſhelter them, but that, I ſay, it hinders not their way of gain, as they underſtand M. <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles</hi> Books, Doctrins, or Opinions do, which makes them ſo maliciouſly zealous againſt him, and to let the others go ſcot-free.</p>
            <p>Magiſtrates were they thus rightly informed of the condition of theſe informers, and thus ſtrongly armed againſt ſuch clamorous zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, they would not ſo ſuddenly, nor ſo reproachfully diſpoſe of the perſons of men fearing God, as throughout all former times was la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably done, and ſomwhat too much in Mr. <hi>Bidles</hi> caſe; they would then have time to deliberate upon the matter, before they ſent a man to priſon, they then, no doubt, would exerciſe their own judgments, as Chriſtians, and ſee what is alledged againſt any man, and deal as becometh Chriſtian Magiſtrates, according to the known and revealed Word of Chriſt manifeſted in the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Which word of Truth, being not <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>nay,</hi> as Parliaments, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councels, Synods, and Aſſemblies have all proved in the moſt material points in Religion, as your Honors, the Bench, and Jury cannot but effectually know<hi>:</hi> For one Councel determining that the Son of God was the moſt high God, another Councel, as namely that of <hi>Ariminum,</hi> conſiſting of no leſs then four hundred Biſhops, decrees point blank <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>as we are wont to ſay) againſt the former, that the Son of God was not the moſt high God, but a diſtinct Eſſence from him, and ſubordinate unto him. This inſtance, amongſt many, have I produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150094:4"/>
to ſhew the mutability of Councels, as alſo to ſhew how cautious you ſhould be of putting to death a learned man for that opinion, which ſo many learned and famous men, not only have been, but ſtill are in the world of his opinion, as you ſhall hear, if you enquire of thoſe who have been in <hi>Poland, Holland, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This bleſſed unerring rule, (viz. the holy Scripture) to Conſcience, being ſincerely looked into, it will impartially diſcover, both to Judg and Jury, what M. <hi>Bidles</hi> opinions are, and how he is to be dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all concerning them, without a ſingle ear given, whereunto the Laws of Parliaments may ſo on cauſe you all to be moſt grievous tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Laws of God, and to be more guilty in his ſight, before whom one day you muſt all be judged, then thoſe Priſoners you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn. Whatſoever therefore the Law of the Lord ſayes to your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings in this caſe of M. <hi>Bidles,</hi> let none by no arts draw you from enquiring into the Seriptures for ſatisfaction in every particular.</p>
            <p>In which enquiry, though your Honor, Mr. Recorder, and the whole Honorable Bench are all highly concerned to look unto it, that you may acquit your ſelves before the judgment ſeat of Chriſt, and be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to render an account with joy.</p>
            <p>Yet you good men of the Jury are more neerly concerned to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act and faithful therein, for it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s your Verdict, your guilty or not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that ſaves, or deſtroys his life, which you are mainly to note, and to lay to heart, and to be all along mindful of it, that if you pronounce him guilty (which God defend) you do not only find him guilty of ſpeaking ſuch or ſuch words, or of writing and publiſhing ſuch or ſuch Books, but in pronouncing him guilty upon either of the Indictments, you pronounce him a Felon, and deſervedly to die; ſo that unleſs in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of your conſciences he appears worthy to die as a Felon, you are in conſcience bound to pronounce him not guilty, otherwiſe you may be his deſtroyers before you are aware, to your perpetual grief and anxiety of ſpirit, for ſo it befel the Jury that were the Tryers of M. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dall,</hi> a worthy Miniſter of Gods Word in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days, he was Indicted for High Treaſon, in making and publiſhing a certain Book againſt the Government of the Biſhops, and though there was no direct, but a ſcambling ſhadow of a proof, and though the Books duly conſidered, contained no colour of Treaſon or other crime, no more then M. <hi>Bidles</hi> of Felony, but ſuch as the times ſince have proved as true as Truth its ſelf, yet the Jury not thinking in pronouncing him guilty, they had pronounced him guilty of Treaſon, and to die as a Traytor, ſuppoſing they had only declared him guilty of making the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150094:4"/>
Book, hereupon they brought him in guilty; but when after the Judges ſentence of death againſt him, which they never in the leaſt intended, that they found what they had done, they were confounded in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and would have done any thing in the world to have revoked their Verdict, when alas it was too late, and therefore you are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding careful in this main particular; never to pronounce him guilty, unleſs your conſciences are firſt ſatisfied he ought not to live, but to die as a Felon, which is altogether impoſſible, if you ſhall ſeriouſly and deliberately weigh all circumſtances touching the man &amp; his opinions.</p>
            <p>For firſt, as to the man, he is ſo free from being queſtioned for any the leaſt blemiſh in his life and converſation, that the Informers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have been heard to admire his ſtrickt exemplar life, full of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, ſobriety and forbearance, no ways contentious touching the great things of the world, but altogether taken up with the things of God revealed in the holy Scriptures, wherein his ſtudy, diligence, and attainments have been ſo great, that his knowledg therein is of as ready uſe as a Concordance, no part thereof being named, but he preſently cites the Book, Chapter, and ver. eſpecially throughout the Books of the New Teſtament, where all the Epiſtles he can ſay by heart out of the Greek Tongue, and withal can read the Greek in Engliſh, and the Engliſh in Greek ſo readily, as a man can do the meer Engliſh, ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully hath he been rightly to underſtand them. As to the Juſtice and integrity of his heart, his wayes have manifeſted, that he would not diſſemble, play the Hypocrite, or deal fraudulently with any man to ſave his life; ſuch is he certainly, as is known to very many perſons of worth and credit in <hi>London,</hi> ſo as he is far from being ſuch a Monſter as many have believed him to be, through the uncomely and unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-like clamours of his Accuſers.</p>
            <p>For his opinions you have heard at large, and frequently with what he is charged not to believe, be pleaſed to be ſo juſt to your ſelves and him, as to give ear, and ſeriouſly to note what he profeſſeth, and is known to believe, there being a cloud of Witneſſes ready to teſtifie that he makes it his glory to confeſs with his mouth the Lord Jeſus to be his Lord and his God, according to the Scripture, <hi>John</hi> 20.28. to be his Saviour, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. and by him doth believe in God, who raiſed him from the dead, and gave him glory, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. Having ſet him at his right hand, Angels, Authorities, and Powers being made ſubject to him; and that he is made unto us of God, Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Redemption, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.30. That he is the only begotten Son of God, and to be honored as the Father, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.23. that it is he that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150094:5"/>
is ordained of God to be Judg of quick and dead, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.41. that he is the Author of eternal life to all thoſe that obey him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. that there is no other name under heaven given among men, whereby we muſt be ſaved, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12. that his Blood is the Blood of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that is ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.18. and that he is able to ſave them to the uttermoſt that come unto God by him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. How then, or upon what ground can any man juſtly term him a Blaſphemer? he conceiveth to be according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; if further then this he underſtands not, and for want of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding perceiveth not the Scriptures, do maintain Chriſt the Son to be coequal, coeternal, and coeſſential with God the Father, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhould deny Chriſt to be the moſt high God, ſhall he be put to death for it? Surely none can ſuppoſe a man of ſo much learning, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and piety, can do this maliciouſly, with full purpoſe to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor the Lord Chriſt, whom he ſo much truſteth in, and honoreth, as is before expreſſed; nay, can it be ſuppoſed, but that he who attributes ſo much honor to him, as thoſe Scriptures forecited manifeſt, would with all his ſoul render him all whatſoever by any other Scriptures he underſtood to be his due? nay, the leaſt meaſure of charity may very readily admit, that if ſuch a pious man as he is deny him any part of honor, that he doth it, becauſe he conceives that granting of it would be to his diſhonor, and that he did believe he would be much diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have it attributed unto him; ſhall this fear, and warineſs in him find (admit that it were evidently an Error in his judgment) no lower title then Blaſphemy? and for this, will nothing ſatisfie the Informers but his life? What thoughts have theſe men of the Lord Chriſt, that came not to deſtroy, but to ſave mens lives? that will not break the bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax; that called not the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces</hi> Blaſphemers, nor Heretikes, nor denounced judgment upon them, either of impriſonment or death, no though they came to tempt him, though they denied the Reſurrection, and ſaid, there was neither Angel nor Spirit; yea ſo far was our moſt merciful Lord Chriſt from ſo harſh a ſpirit, that he ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 12.47, 48. <hi>If any man hear my words, and believe not them, I judg him not, the word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judg him at the last day:</hi> and rebuketh thoſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 54. who through a raſh unadviſed zeal, (much like what at beſt appeareth in theſe Proſecutors) that would have called for fire from heaven to have conſumed the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Yo know not what ſpirit you are of;</hi> a ſentence worthy to be written in letters of Gold, in every place of Judicature in the world, but eſpecially in the hearts of all men truſted; as you are, with the lives of men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150094:5"/>
               <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> are allowed, in order to their converſion, to ask any queſtions concerning God, Chriſt, or the Holy Spirit, to affirm, or deny, as they ſee cauſe, without being termed Blaſphemers for ſo doing, yea, rather pity their miſtakings; nay the Jews that ſpeak ſuch opprobrious language of Chriſt, as is not fit to be repeated, denying not only his Godhead, but his moſt holy and heavenly Conception, yet are they not impriſoned, nor Indicted for Blaſphemers, nor moleſted, but ſuffered to live quietly amongſt us, for which way elſe ſhall they ever be converted to the Faith of Chriſt? Why then is it ſo hainous a thing in M. <hi>Bidle</hi> to ſay he doth deny this or that opinion of Chriſt, to that end it may be proved by Scripture? Why doth not ſome zealous perſon ſhew him wherein he is miſtaken, without calling him a Blaſphemer? Will it ſuffize to quit a man from the guilt of ſuch an ignominious appellation, to believe every ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Apoſtles Creed, if it will, it is then moſt certain this good man Mr. <hi>Bidle,</hi> believes all and every Article thereof, in every reſpect, as they are there expreſſed? If this will not ſuffize, but that <hi>Athenaſius</hi> his Creed muſt in every circumſtance be believed alſo, or thoſe that cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, and conſequently cannot believe it in all points, ſhall be deemed Blaſphemers, by moſt, aſſuredly it would be thought too harſh a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for do you but obſerve with what ſatisfaction, with how much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacrity the conſcience cloſeth with the former ſaying, <hi>I believe in God, the Father Almighty, maker of heaven and earth, and in Jeſus Chriſt his onely Son our Lord, which was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, born of the</hi> Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>ſuffered under</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>was crucified, dead, and buried, deſcended into hell, the third day he aroſe again from the dead, and aſcended into heaven, and ſitteth at the right hand of God, the Father Almighty, from thence he ſhall come to judge both the quick and the dead: I believe in the Holy Ghost, the Holy Catholique Church, the Communion of Saints, the forgiveneſs of ſins, the Reſurrection of the body, and the life ever laſting.</hi> There being no Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of this Belief, (as Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> uſeth to affirm) but that even in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it preſents a plain place of Scripture to the minde for proofe thereof.</p>
            <p>Whereas in reciting that of <hi>Athenaſius,</hi> (which was the ground of that Ordinance of the Lords and Commons, in making it Blaſphemy to affirm ſo, and ſo, concerning Chriſt and the Holy Spirit) what infinite doubts and ſcruples do ariſe? as where it is ſaid, <hi>For there is one perſon of the Father, another of the Son, and another of the Holy Ghoſt, but the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt is all one, the glory equal, the Majeſty coeternal; ſuch as the Father, ſuch is the Son and ſuch is the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt; the Father uncreate, the Son uncreate, and the Holy Ghoſt uncreate,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150094:6"/>
               <hi>the Father incomprehenſible, the Son incomprehenſible, and the Holy Ghost in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible; the Father eternal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Son eternal and the Holy Ghoſt eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and yet they are not three eternals but one eternal; as alſo there are not three incomprehenſibles, nor three uncreated, but one uncreated. and one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible; ſo likew ſe the Father is almighty, the Son almighty, and the Holy Ghoſt almighty; and yet there are not three almighties, but one almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c. And in this Trinity none is before nor after another, none is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or leſſer then another, but the whole three perſons be coeternal toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and coequal, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is true, moſt men of years living in this Nation, have through breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cuſtome been formerly uſed to recite this Creed, as what they did believe, but how few there were that did truly underſtand it, that is, that did truly believe what they ſaid, and ſeemed to believe, you can now very eaſily judg; nay how glad would al ingenuous Chriſtians be, that theſe difficulties might without danger be clearly diſcuſſed, by ſtrength of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, that ſo men might no longer have things run in their mind, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved by them, which in deed and in truth they do not underſtand, nor are able to render a reaſon of the hope that is in them, touching many of the particulars, which is no better then hypocriſie and groſs ſuperſtition, for though men may hide their hearts from men, yet from themſelves, and from God they cannot hide them.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe Mr <hi>Bidle</hi> hath laboured in this work, to enquire how theſe obſcure difficult expreſſions in this Creed are proved in Scripture, which he taketh for the foundation of his faith; and becauſe he hath not been contented to take up other opinions concerning God, according to the current of Interpreters of our times, but ſtill ground himſelf upon the Scripture, for this cauſe only is he now a priſoner, and for no other; for this cauſe, and none other, doth his Accuſers, the Informers, deem him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to live.</p>
            <p>But it is hoped with you he will find a much more charitable and Chriſtian eſteem, for what at worſt can be alledged againſt him, or what can warrant the taking away of his life.</p>
            <p>For admit the words or Books ſhould be fully proved againſt him, and that you ſhould think ſuch Accuſers and Witneſſes worthy of belief, when not the glory of God, or of Chriſt, but their own gain hath ſet them on.</p>
            <p>Admit that mens lives may be taken away by an Ordinance of the Lords and Commons, out of time of Parliament, which will not be granted, <hi>England</hi> being to be ruled by Acts, not Ordinances, ſo as therein alſo the foundation fails, for he is tried upon no other but an Ordinance. Again, ſuppoſe the Ordinance, Law, there is nothing of obſtinacy expreſſed in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150094:6"/>
Indictment againſt Mr. <hi>Bidle,</hi> without which he doth not offend againſt it; but were the Ordinance in force, it directs the priſoner to be Indicted the next Goal delivery, but M. <hi>Bidle</hi> was not Indicted till the ſecond Goal delivery, after complaint and impriſonment, wherefore the Ordinance is not purſued, but the time prefixed elapſed. Yet further, admit there were an Act, and in force, yet that a Parliament can be truſted in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Conſcience, the Scripture never warranted, men cannot truſt, becauſe they muſt obey, not what Parliaments eſtabliſh, but what the Scripture ſaith to their particular Conſciences; ſo as if Parliaments under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Scriptures one way, and you another, whether are you to yeeld to their ſenſe or your own? whether are you to believe and worſhip as they direct, or as you judg your ſelves directed by the Word of God? ſo that the making of Laws by Parliaments in matters of Religion, Faith, and Gods Worſhip, which God never did, and men cannot truſt them withal, ſo that although this Ordinance were an Act, and were not annihilated by the inſtrument of Government, as indeed it is in Mr. <hi>Bidles</hi> caſe, you could not with innocent conſciences find him guilty upon it. If Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> be not protected by the inſtrument, none are; for you will find it evidently intended by the 36. 37. and 38. Articles, which ſay thus<hi>:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>36 That to the publique profeſſion held forth, none ſhall be compelled by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, or otherwiſe, but that endeavours be uſed to win them by ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and the example of a good converſation.</p>
            <p>37 That ſuch as profeſs Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt (though differing in judgment from the doctrine, worſhip, or diſcipline publikely held forth) ſhall not be reſtrained from, but ſhall be protected in the profeſſion of the Faith, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Religion ſo as they abuſe not this liberty, to the civil injury of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to the actual diſturbance of the Publike Peace on their parts, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this liberty be not extended to Popery or Prelacy, nor to ſuch, as under the profeſſion of Christ, hold forth and practiſe licentiouſneſs.</p>
            <p>38 That all Laws, Statutes, Ordinances, and clauſes in any Law, Statute, and Ordinance to the contrary of the aforeſaid liberty, ſhall be eſteemed as null and void.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> now profeſſeth Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt, and that truly, not notionally; and as the compilers of the inſtrument by their words ſhew us they did intend<hi>:</hi> As for Popery, Prelacy, teaching or practiſing licentiouſneſs, ſo free is he from theſe, as none taxeth him with it, How then can it be, that his differing in judgment from the doctrine, worſhip, or diſcipline publikely held forth, ſhould exclude him any more then any other man in the Nation from protection in the profeſſion of the Faith, and exerciſe of his Religion, ſince he no way abuſeth this liberty, to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150094:7"/>
civil injury of others, nor doth any thing to the diſturbance of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Peace on his part, but on the contrary, demeaneth himſelf peaceably and quietly, as becometh a Chriſtian, and exhorteth others to do the like.</p>
            <p>The true ſenſe and meaning of theſe Articles, or of the intention of the Law-makers thereof, you can no otherwiſe know, from any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, ſo as to be ſatisfactory to your conſciences, but from the words and expreſſions themſelves which do moſt evidently and plainly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford M <hi>Bidle</hi> protection from all Laws and Ordinances before made, and from all kinds of trouble and moleſtation.</p>
            <p>As for proving any the opinions alledged againſt him to be Blaſphemy in the Scripture ſenſe, is impoſſible to be made appear.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> a Blaſphemer was to be put to death, and you hear often that Scripture urged, to incite you to judg ſuch to death, as are at any time indicted here for Blaſphemy; but you are to be aware of Scripture miſapplied, there being no ſpeedier way to miſery and deſtruction, Chriſtians being not to be ſwayed in their judgments and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences by the rule of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but by the precepts and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: Yet if Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> were to be tried by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> unleſs it do appear, that by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> theſe things, or words, or books in the Indictments are declared to be Blaſphemies, or ſuch crimes, as for which men ought to die (which that declareth not) there would be no ground at all from thence to proceed againſt him.</p>
            <p>And as for any warrant from the New Teſtament, you have heard al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready how gently Chriſt himſelf dealt with the misbelieving <hi>Sadduces;</hi> as alſo with thoſe that would not receive his Word, and how he reproved ſuch as would have had fire from heaven to conſume the <hi>Samaritans;</hi> ſo as from thence nothing will ever juſtly be raiſed to endanger his life in your hands, nay, not to countenance his leaſt moleſtation.</p>
            <p>For let the utmoſt that can be urged from theſe places, by the miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of which, many a well meaning Judg and Jury man hath been in this place miſled, to the ſad deſtruction of many innocent men fearing God, for the daies are ſtill in remembrance, and will never be forgotten, whenas Parliaments were ſo unchriſtianlike buſie in making Laws in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, touching Faith, and the Worſhip of God, that amongſt other ſnares laid to intrap good mens lives, they enacted to this effect, <hi>That whoſoever ſhould deny the very Body and Blood of Christ to be really in the Bread and Wine, after the words of Conſecration, ſhould be put to death, as being an Heretique or Blaſphemer.</hi> Whereupon divers Informers of thoſe times ſet themſelves, and were by the then Clergy ſecretly put on, to lay in wait, and gather up ſuch words, as rendred enquiring Chriſtians,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150094:7"/>
which were willing to be ſatisfied of the truth of ſo ſtrange a myſtery ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctious to their cruelty, moſt of the Informers being Bookſellers, whoſe trade was ſure to fail, in caſe this myſtery, of which their Books were full ſtuffed, ſhould be proved but a deluſion, beſtirred themſelves to purpoſe, halling and driving multitudes before the Biſhops, who ſoon ſentenced them, and turned them over to the civil Magiſtrates, to be put to death for Blaſphemy and Hereſie.</p>
            <p>Where by the way, your Honor, and the Honorable Bench, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally you good men of the Jury, are to obſerve with what reverence, nay, with what adoration, this error, this the groſſeſt error in all Popery, (as Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> uſeth to call it) was every where believed, and no marvel when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Parliament Law had made it death to diſpute or deny it; and then how here in <hi>England,</hi> where liberty of debating and diſputing this myſterious point hath been long time admitted; this groſs error hath been wrought out of moſt mens underſtandings, (which effectually ſheweth the real ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and benefit of freedome in diſpute, and arguing of all points, none excepted; and what enemy to the truth thoſe are, this Chriſtian liberty) yet ſtill to this day, where Laws of State govern in matters of Religion, and where conſcience and diſcourſes are overawed with Laws of Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Baniſhments, and death, as in moſt of the Popiſh Dominions they are, there this groſſe error, which now through Gods mercy appears to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very conſiderate perſon one of the greateſt and moſt palpable myſteries of iniquity, is nevertheleſſe admitted, and received with the ſame, if not high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er reſpect and admiration then ever, which ſhews alſo of what Tribe and Kindred they are, that would have ſetled here again in this Nation a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive or conſtraining power in matters of conſcience, belief, and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God.</p>
            <p>And truly, whil'ſt you have this myſterious point of the real preſence of Chriſts Fleſh and Blood in the Sacrament, and cannot but wonder how it ſhould enter into mans heart to be believed, it being ſo expreſly contrary to every ones perſeverance, taſting therein very Bread, and very Wine, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven after the words of Conſecration. whilſt you have this in mind, and through how many difficulties, and impoſſibilities, and wrackings of the underſtanding by Sophiſmes and ſubtil arguments, men were made to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that they did believe the real preſence to be there, when it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any, though they ſaid they did ſo much as to underſtand it, for ſo groſſe an error did never appear a reality or truth to the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Be pleaſed, whilſt your thoughts are thus imployed, to reflect upon the opinions which are charged upon M. <hi>Bidle,</hi> which for more eaſie conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preſent themſelves in this form, <hi>That he is indicted as a Blaſphemer, for denying the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Trinity, and the Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, that the Father is the</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150094:8"/>
               <hi>most high God, the Son the moſt high God, and the Holy Ghoſt the moſt high God, and theſe are not three moſt high Gods, but one moſt high God.</hi> This any man may affirm he believeth, and moſt men do affirm they do believe it, and it is like the Informers would not ſcruple to ſwear they do believe it, as thoſe of the former times, no doubt, would have ſworn, they both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and believed the real preſence in the Sacrament; but dealing clearly and conſcientiouſly with your own hearts, Is not this a myſtery moſt difficult to be underſtood? Can any thing be more myſterious? Do you i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that one of an hundred underſtands it, who yet through fear of the Law, and awe of death, ſayes he believes it? Is any point in Chriſtianity more obſcure in Scripture? Why did not <hi>Athenaſius</hi> affix thoſe places of Scripture to his Creed, upon which he grounds his judgment; whereas in place whereof, he gives you only this for proof, That as we be compelled by the <hi>Christian verity</hi> to believe, what in this his Creed he affirms ought to be believed, ſo, ſaith he, are we forbidden by the <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> to acknowledg whatſoever he therein denies. Now you know the Real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence was a long time here taken for a main part of <hi>Chriſtian verity,</hi> and men were interdicted and forbidden, under pain of death, to deny it by the <hi>Catholike Religion;</hi> (for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was thought to be no leſſe then the Catholike unerring Church) ſo as this his <hi>Christian verity,</hi> and this his <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> are in theſe times of enquiry but ſlender proofs, and may very well admit of diſpute, and a demand of plain Scripture proof to prove them, and it is a very hard caſe if men for argument ſake may not deny any thing <hi>Athenaſius</hi> therein affirms, or affirm any thing he therein denies, the purpoſe and intention being to ſee what Scriptures can be brought for full proof of the things diſputed; nay, if any conſcientious Chriſtian ſhall really think <hi>Athenaſius</hi> miſtaken in his myſterious opinions, what offence is it to declare his thoughts, and to deny them? Every one knows by <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> truth comes to be eſtabliſhed, it is only error that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires no arguments or diſputations, but that of Law, and the Sword on its ſide, unhallowed weapons to combat with error, truth being ever Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſher where thoſe odds are not: It is not denied, that the moſt myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous opinions may be true, but it muſt be only Scripture that proves them ſo, and then if freedom of diſpute and argument be allowed, the more theſe truths are oppoſed or denied, the clearer the truth ever appeareth, truth being like that houſe built upon the Rock, that ſtands the firmer for being aſſaulted; error like the houſe built upon the Sand, which had need keep oppoſition far from her by the out works of Law, and threats of death, for ſo you ſee it ſpeeds beſt and continues longeſt, as that abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable error of the Real Preſence, which whilſt hedged about by Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Law, was with the ſlighteſt arguments, and even with Scriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150094:8"/>
able, and did even in this place deprive many of Gods dear ones of their liberties, yea of their very lives, by the moſt cruel tormenting deaths their malicious Proſecutors and Informers could deviſe.</p>
            <p>An Heretique he was that denied the Real Preſence, that the Parliament Law enacted, and an Heretique or Blaſphemer muſt be put to death, that alſo the Parliament took care for: They alſo made the poor beſotted ſuperſtitious people believe, that it ſuffized not, except the Scriptures war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted it; and therefore they never failed to urge the Scripture in <hi>Titus</hi> 3.10 11. <hi>A man that is an Heretique after the firſt and ſecond admonition, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, knowing that he that is ſuch is ſubverted and ſinneth, being condemned of himſelf:</hi> So then, ſay they, (as ſome will not fail to apply it to M. <hi>Bidle)</hi> the Priſoner at the Bar is an Heretique, why? for he denieth the Body and Blood of Chriſt to be really and corporally in the Sacrament; ſo ſuch an one is a ſinner, and perverted from the Chriſtian verity, and from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion, and is condemned of him ſelf: Yes, ſaith the Arch-biſhop, it is impoſſible but he muſt condemn himſelf, his evil is ſo palpable, only he is obſtinate, and will not acknowledg or confeſſe it: Well then, what is to be done with ſuch an Heretique? Why, the Scripture ſaith, after the firſt and ſecond admonition reject. We and our Clergy have admoniſhed him often and again, to forſake his wicked Hereſie, yet ſtill he perſiſts, therefore is to be rejected, that is, ſay they, and the ignorant ſeduced Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of thoſe times believed them, let him be put to death; yea, ſay they, the Scripture is plain, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12. <hi>I would they were even cut off then trouble you:</hi> which though every conſcientious Chriſtian knew in the Apoſtles ſenſe never intended more then an Excommunication, as doth alſo the forecited reject; yet theſe falſe counterfeiting Apoſtles never failed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret, a cutting off by death. But to ſtrengthen theſe further, they urge 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. with great vehemency againſt the poor innocents, <hi>But there were falſe Prophets alſo among the people, even as there ſhall be falſe teachers among you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift destruction.</hi> This nail they drive home into the Saints Temples, crying out, <hi>Theſe are they that deny the Lord that bought them,</hi> for they deny him to be corporally preſent in the Holy Sacrament, away with them to fire and faggot, <hi>for they bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſwift deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this place of Scripture was ſo violently urged in the late Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Mr. <hi>Bidle,</hi> and made, or ſeemed to make ſo deep an impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the very zealous part of them, that they were even ready to Vote upon a ſwift and ſudden death, and were very hardly with-held from it, nay, had done it, but that the more conſcientious amongſt them replied ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, that this place of Scripture could not poſſibly be applied to M. <hi>Bidle,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:150094:9"/>
it being evident that he was ſo far from denying the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to be the Lord that bought him, or from denying him to be the Meſſiah, the Chriſt, the Redeemer, that all the writings called his, and his diſcourſes, did manifeſt that he did believe in his heart, and confeſſe with his mouth the Lord Jeſus to be his Lord and his God (as afore is more largely expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) which if it ſhall pleaſe you to conſider, together with what in the third ver. is ſaid of the falſe Teachers, viz. <hi>and through covetouſneſs ſhall they with feigned words make Merchandize of you,</hi> ye will find it reaches not Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> in the leaſt, none in the world being more free from the loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſin of covetouſneſſe, or from making Merchandize of any, every one that knows him, knoweth that he having food and rayment, is therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all content, and that he (if any one in the world) accounts godlineſſe with content, the greateſt gain in, ſo as when all the whole Scriptures are ſearched for matter againſt Mr. <hi>Bidle,</hi> let them be but impartially conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they will appear no more in juſtification of his moleſtation impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, or further puniſhment, then they were in approving the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous cruelties inflicted upon thoſe former ſufferers.</p>
            <p>So that upon your ſerious conſideration of all things, it cannot be doubted, but that Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> is as ſafe, whilſt your Chriſtian conſciences thus rightly informed, ſtand between him and death, as if he were at his own diſpoſing, and being ſo through your godly care of him, you will acquit your ſelves as wiſe and diſcreet Chriſtians in the ſight of God, and ſtanch that innocent Blood, which hath violently been let run formerly in this place upon like occaſions, and free both your ſelves, your poſterity, and this Honorable City from Judgments and plagues due for the ſame. Now the God of peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Jeſus, that great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, make you perfect in every good work to do his will, working in you that which is well pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be glory for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
